People at the CIA are there for 25, 30, 35 years.
They're unelected.
There's no accountability to pretty much anyone.
And they know that they can outweigh presidents.
If there's a president that they don't like,
like Donald Trump, they don't have to do what he says.
They just slow-roll whatever orders come from the White House
and end up at Langley.
If there's one lesson that I learned at the CIA,
it's that the CIA will push the envelope
all the way into illegality unless somebody pushes back.
I have said is that this campaign
is not just about electing a president.
It is about making a political revolution.
And tea.
Taking money from our children
and borrowing from China.
People are dying.
Is the program so critical
it's worth borrowing money from China to pay for it?
And if not, I'll get rid of it.
Stop lying and the truth!
Avoid the apocalypse altogether.
Here's another episode of Macro and Cheese
with your host, Steve Grumbine.
All right.
Yes, this is Steve Grumbine with Macro and Cheese this week.
I have another whistleblower.
I've got a guy who has been on the inside
seen what the belly of the beast looks like,
came outside and has not been able to stop talking about it since.
I'm speaking about John Kiriakou,
who is a former CIA officer,
former senior investigator for the Senate Farm Relations Committee
and former counterterrorism consultant for ABC News.
He was responsible for the capture in Pakistan in 2002
of Abu Zabudai,
believed to be the third ranking official in Al Qaeda.
In 2007, Kiriakou blew the whistle on the CIA's torture program,
saying the CIA tortured prisoners
that torture was official U.S. government policy
and that the policy had been approved by then-President George W. Bush.
He became the sixth whistleblower indicted
by the Obama administration under the Espionage Act,
a law designed to punish spies.
He served 23 months in prison as a result of the revelation.
Kiriakou won the Joseph A. Callaway Award
for Civic Courage in 2012,
Penn Center USA's prestigious First Amendment Award in 2015,
the first blueprint for free speech international whistleblowing prize
for bravery and integrity in the public interest in 2016,
and the Sam Adams Award for integrity and intelligence,
also in 2016.
Kiriakou is the author of The Reluctant Spy,
My Secret Life in the CIA's War on Terror,
doing time like a spy,
how the CIA taught me to survive and thrive in prison,
and the convenient terrorist and Abu Zabadi
and the weird wonderland of America's secret wars.
And without further ado, let me bring on my guest, John.
Welcome to the show, sir.
Thank you, Steve.
Good to be with you.
Normally, I'm on the other side of the mic here
when I'm with you in political misfits.
Yeah.
One of the things that we didn't say there
is that you're the co-host with my dear friend Michelle Whitty
as well.
And that's always a pleasure.
So thanks for having me on all those times.
I don't know.
It's wonderful.
We love having you.
Thanks for doing it.
Absolutely.
One of the reasons why I brought you in here,
I think everybody that has become politically active since,
let's say, 2015,
because there was a lot of stuff that happened in Occupy.
But I think a large group of people
that had previously never sniffed the world of politics
came alive when Bernie Sanders ran in 2015
against Hillary Clinton.
Then we saw the Donald Trump regime.
Then we saw Bernie run again.
Joe Biden was selected by the Democratic Party.
And I think a lot of people have been through the mill
watching their hearts desires and their dreams
and their hopes get smashed along the rocky shores of democracy.
And I think people just genuinely believe
that this is just the way it is
and that there is no alternative
and that people are otherwise just assuming
that they have no power.
And part of that is not by accident.
Part of that is the stuff that goes on behind the scenes
by unelected bureaucrats
and other spy-like agencies
such as the CIA,
which you are intimately familiar with,
not just in the United States, but globally.
In a prior interview with Chris Hedges
that was listened to or seen by nearly half million people,
one of the key things that you brought out
was a senator who had kind of left you high and dry
during your time when you had come out and been brave
and he ignored you.
And when you confronted him with it,
his concern was that he was going to lose his clearance
that the CIA had eyes on him
and that terror that he felt,
the way I understand it based on some of your work,
seems like that's not a isolated incident.
That seems to be like an unelected body
is hovering over our elected representatives.
And so beyond the idea of democracy failing us,
there's a deep state that control the levers of power
that go beyond the theater that is politics.
So often, Steve, people believe
that this is a right-wing trope
and it's not.
It's a fact of everyday life here in the United States.
The week that Donald Trump became president
in January of 2017, I got a call from CNN
and they asked if I would come on
and talk about this back and forth
that Trump had been having with the CIA.
And you might remember this
where Senate Majority Leader,
what's his name from New York?
Chuck Schumer?
Yes.
Where the Senate Majority Leader had warned Trump
not to take on the CIA
because he said they have nine ways from Sunday
for getting back at you.
And so CNN had me on and they wanted to know
what he meant by that.
And I said, well, it's not November 22nd, 1963
because that's what people were jumping up
and shouting about.
What it was was you look at presidents.
Presidents are only president for four years or eight years.
People at the CIA are there for 25, 30, 35 years.
They're unelected.
There's no accountability to pretty much anyone.
And they know that they can outweigh presidents.
If there's a president that they don't like
like Donald Trump,
they don't have to do what he says.
They just slow roll whatever orders come from the White House
and end up at Langley.
If they don't want to do a covert action program,
let's say they just move slowly,
knowing that in four years he's going to be gone
or worst case scenario, eight years he's going to be gone.
Now, one of the other things that the CIA does
and they're very, very good at this
is recruiting in air quotes, recruiting new presidents.
The CIA especially loves it when a president is elected
who has little or no intelligence experience.
Because what happens is literally the day after the election,
the PDB staff, the president's daily brief staff begins
to brief the new president-elect
with the same briefing that the president himself gets.
Now, when I was there, there were only 11 people
who were entitled to a daily PDB briefing.
So it's the president, the vice president,
the secretaries of state and defense,
the National Security Advisor,
a handful of people in the National Security Council
and that's pretty much it.
So when you've got a brand new young, inexperienced president,
you go to him the day after the election
or her, whatever the case happens to be
and you say, Mr. President, Madam President,
your first briefing,
just wait until you see the cool things
that we are doing all around the world.
Wait until you see this blue border report
that's classified at four levels above top secret
or black border report that's eyes only for the president.
And you've sort of sucked them in
to this little club that we all had
where this stuff is so important and so secret
that nobody else can know about it.
Isn't it cool?
Isn't it great to be one of us now?
And you've done it.
You've sucked them in.
And as it ends up,
there are the ones running foreign policy,
not the president.
There are the ones telling elected overseers on Capitol Hill
how things are going to be,
not the overseers themselves.
The CIA is very, very good
doing this kind of thing.
They've been doing it really since the 60s,
since the 50s even.
With the recent non-disclosure of the Kennedy assassination,
it was heavily redacted what little came out.
It's quite clear regardless of whether or not
you believe the CIA was involved
in taking out a president,
then activists,
then political leaders like Martin Luther King Jr.
or breaking up the Black Panthers
or whether it be attacking Occupy Wall Street.
These people are unelected bureaucrats
or unelected soldiers in a sense.
Right.
It explains in many ways
why no matter who gets elected,
it really all stays the same.
Yeah, that's absolutely right.
This may seem like a few years late,
but I want to get a definitive answer.
Define what the deep state is and is not.
Yeah, to me, it's actually pretty simple.
To viewers of Fox News and OAN and Newsmax,
it probably isn't very simple.
To me, it is those unelected officials
who run the day-to-day operation
of the country's foreign policy,
defense policy,
intelligence policy.
It's really quite easy.
The way modern government has been set up
is that it's not supposed to be like that.
You've got the executive branch,
you've got experts within the executive branch,
and then you're supposed to have the legislative branch
that is overseeing all of this.
And in many cases,
especially in that of the CIA,
it just doesn't work that way.
But I'm not allowed to say how many people are in the CIA.
The number is classified,
but it's tens of thousands of people
with a multi-billion-dollar budget.
And you've got about a dozen and a half people
on the Senate side
and maybe another two dozen on the House side
that oversee this gargantuan organization.
And it just simply doesn't work.
Now, the story that you opened with
I think is an important one
and it bears a little bit of explanation.
When I got out of prison,
I ran into this senator at a dinner party
and I went up to him and I said,
hey senator, I gotta say,
I was disappointed that you didn't come out
in support of me.
You should have been,
in my view, a natural ally.
He got very angry.
He got right in my face about it.
He goes, look,
it took all of my energy
just to not lose my security clearance.
And boy, that just made everything so clear to me.
Here you are,
one of the senior most members
of the Senate Intelligence Committee.
You're supposed to be the boss,
the one overseeing the CIA
and you are afraid of them.
You're afraid that because you came down
on a certain side of a political issue,
they're going to take your security clearance away.
That's just cowardice,
but it also goes to show you
the long arm of the CIA.
I've been doing a lot of research
on everything from the Bolshevik Revolution
to present,
largely focusing recently
on what happened post World War Two
and the effects of combating
then what they saw as Joseph Stalin's
empire building desires
and the act of trying to counter communism
became everything.
You already had McCarthy.
You had so many things
that it becomes so toxic to society.
But I think this is not the beginning
of the deep state,
but I think this is the beginning
of seeing it in its nascent state,
Truman battling with MacArthur
and MacArthur wanting to take
the Korean War into China,
into Russia,
willing to do whatever it could
to put the death stake
into the heart of communism.
And it took everything Truman had
and I'm not here to defend
or celebrate Truman.
I think it's pretty fair to say
he's a mass murderer,
but he had to stand up
against his general and relieve him
of duty popular military guy.
So Truman says,
thank you and brings him home.
Yeah, replaces him.
But it almost cost Truman
his presidency.
It definitely cost him a lot of clout.
A lot of people really angry at the move.
That was a blatant,
very visible act of the understate
at the time.
Yes.
Standing against the sitting president
and doing their own thing,
behaving as if they're the kings of the world,
minus being elected to be in that role.
Is that the beginning of this departure
or has this been going on even further back?
It started earlier than that.
There was a movement within the military
in the mid 1930s
to essentially overthrow Franklin Roosevelt.
Wow.
And then nothing ended up coming of it
and several generals were forced into retirement.
You're a hundred percent right
about MacArthur and Truman.
There were rumblings during the Vietnam War
of Westmoreland.
Yes, exactly.
Even before Westmoreland.
Yes, Westmoreland was one.
The other one was George Wallace's running mate.
The general who said he wanted to turn
North Vietnam into glass.
Curtis LeMay.
Yeah, we actually had to worry
about that kind of thing
until the end of the Vietnam War.
But now, Steve, it's as though the deep state
has evolved to a point
where they're more sophisticated than that.
They know better than to do it publicly
out in the open.
They know that they're far more powerful
behind the scenes,
doing it quietly.
That's why as recently as the 1980s,
we had people like Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan
sponsoring votes of no confidence
in sitting CIA directors.
We would never see something like that today.
Now the Senate and House Intelligence Committees
are really little more than cheerleaders for the CIA.
Post 9 11, nobody would dream of challenging the CIA.
Let me point to the torture program
and it's not just the torture program.
We can talk about the rendition program,
the secret prison program.
We can talk about a whole bunch of different things.
But the oversight committees were fully informed
that these programs were going on.
The oversight committees knew that these programs were illegal.
At least they were also immoral and unethical.
And do you think a single person objective
and I mean from the left to the right
and everybody in between, nobody objected.
I'll add that through much of the torture program,
the chairman of the House Intelligence Committee
was Jane Harmon, the progressive Democrat
from Venice, California.
Oh my, you think she ever objected to the fact
that we were kidnapping people
and taking them to secret prisons to be tortured
and in some cases, at least to be murdered extra
judicially.
The Democrats never objected.
Nancy Pelosi before she was the speaker
was on the Intelligence Committee.
You think she ever objected?
Nobody ever did.
Is that an indicator of cowardice
or the balance of power between the deep state
and our elected officials?
That's a great question.
And I think it's a combination of the two.
I think that post 9-11 federal elected officials,
regardless of their ideology,
really believe that we're the good guys.
And if the people who know best,
the people who are leading the CIA,
the people who are leading DoD
or the people who are leading
the National Security Council
say that they need X, Y and Z.
Well, then by God,
we're all patriotic Americans
and we're going to give them X, Y and Z.
And I think that that does a disservice
to the American people
because we should question everything.
If there's one thing I learned at the CIA,
one lesson that I learned at the CIA,
it's that the CIA will push the envelope
all the way into illegality
unless somebody pushes back.
Unless somebody on Capitol Hill
or at the National Security Council
or at the Justice Department's
Office of Legal Counsel says,
wait a minute, you can't do that.
It's illegal.
They'll do it.
They have to be told not to
and almost nobody has the guts
to tell them not to.
That brings up a great point.
And I think for those
who don't know this,
let's get back to the beginning of the CIA.
Yeah, when did the CIA
even get spoken into existence?
It's actually relatively recent.
The CIA was created
with the National Security Act of 1947.
And there's kind of a fun story there too
because J. Edgar Hoover,
who was the director of the FBI
since it was created
in the Calvin Coolidge administration
in the 1920s.
He was adamantly opposed
to the creation of the CIA.
He famously hated General Bill Donovan
who was the founder of the CIA's predecessor organization,
the Office of Strategic Services, the OSS.
And Hoover believed for better or worse
that we didn't need a CIA,
that the FBI could do everything
and they were doing everything
as it was in 1947.
And so he was actively lobbying
for no votes on Capitol Hill
that would have defeated the National Security Act of 1947.
And besides creating the CIA,
this act also created the National Security Council.
So President Truman called Hoover into the Oval Office
and said, look, I want you to stop lobbying members of Congress
on the National Security Act.
We need a CIA.
And the deal that they came to
was that Hoover would endorse
the National Security Act
and in exchange,
Truman would make the CIA a division of the FBI.
That was a lie.
He was lying to Hoover.
He never had any intention
of making the CIA division of the FBI.
And so the bill passed.
Truman signed it into law
and after it was all said and done,
Hoover realized that he had been duped
and the CIA was created.
Now, don't forget,
there was no congressional oversight committee
to oversee CIA activities
until 1975.
From 1947 until 1975,
the CIA did literally anything it wanted to do
and there was no one anywhere in government
to tell them no.
Within months of the CIA's creation, for example,
they stole the 1948 Italian elections.
It was the first covert action program
that the CIA carried out.
And then that stretched all the way
through the Vietnam War
and it included governmental over-throws
and MKL drugs,
experimentation on American citizens
with LSD and other drugs,
assassinations of foreign leaders,
attempted assassinations of others.
There were dozens of assassinations,
dozens, including of allies
like the president of South Vietnam,
for example.
So yeah, we had decades of just wanton lawlessness.
I'm going to pull us back to the great financial crisis
that just occurred in 2008, 2009
and you had unelected Wall Street oligarchs
through the revolving door
of what amounts to be these cabinet positions
that advise presidents and help create law
and create the tools of the trade
to regulate Wall Street.
And we saw all these bad actors,
JP Morgan's, Jamie Dimon and others,
the Obama administration and their staff
deeply involved in planting these horrible people
that were doing elite control fraud.
All with an idea that we would have the securities
and exchange committee be able to manage them
or these various watchdog groups
within the government regulate them
and they underfund them.
They understaff them.
I think that to manage all the different businesses
I believe it's the auditors that would handle
that professor Bill Black who famously was the king
of bringing down the savings and loan crisis.
He identified the elite control fraud
to create the environment that allowed everyone
to blow the values of these houses up
through an extremely intricate web
of coercion and corruption.
And then no one gets prosecuted
as the entire economy collapses.
Millions of people destitute losing their homes
and this is in essence an element of the deep state
at work while having an oversight group
that is supposed to have the teeth to manage it
and yet nothing happened.
So the idea of creating a government
so small you can drown it in a bathtub
while having these rogue deep state organizations
being able to do whatever the heck they want to do
who are they serving?
Yeah.
The rules of the game that they're playing by
and the people they're serving are not you and I.
They're someone else somewhere way above our heads.
I'm curious what your take on that is
in terms of the lack of enforcement
and the lack of oversight of the CIA.
Yeah.
Very representative of the lack of oversight
of Wall Street.
It's always underfunded and understaffed
and intentionally weak and feckless.
Oh yeah.
And then at the same time you've got in some cases one
in other cases both political parties demanding
deregulation of pretty much any
and every industry in our economy
whether it's banking or airlines
or trucking or whatever making it that much
more difficult to carry out oversight.
It just doesn't make any sense to me.
It seems like every American would want the most efficient
the most law abiding the most trustworthy government possible
and instead we've implemented national policies
that make that just impossible.
Let's take a look.
Your story with the CIA is remarkable
for the purposes of this program.
I'm going to pretend I don't know any of it
and I don't know nearly enough of it.
So I'd like for you to tell us the story of John Kiriakou.
What was your story and what were the results?
Sure.
Well, I was at the CIA for 15 years.
The first half of my career was in analysis solely on Iraq
and the second half of my career was in counterterrorism
operations starting off pre-911 fighting Euro
communist terrorist groups.
My real focus was on a Greek group called Revolutionary
Organization 17 November and then post 9 11 of course
everybody worked against Al Qaeda.
I ended up going to Pakistan as the chief of counterterrorism
operations at the station there and in that position
I led a series of raids one night in late March 2002
that resulted in the capture of Abu Zubaydah who we believed
at the time was the number three in Al Qaeda.
We also captured again I'm not allowed to say the number
but many dozens of other Al Qaeda fighters that night
and several mid to high ranking leaders of Al Qaeda.
This is a very long story.
I'm going to skip 99% of it in the end.
Abu Zubaydah was sent to a secret prison and he was
tortured there mercilessly.
I was opposed to that torture and when I went back
to CIA headquarters from Pakistan I was asked if I wanted
to be trained in the use of enhanced interrogation techniques
that was one of 14 people who were approached.
I'm sorry to say I regret to say that of the 14 I was the
only one who declined and I said that I had a moral and
ethical problem with it and I believed that it was illegal.
We have very clear laws in this country and we have
since 1946 specifically outlawing exactly the kinds of
techniques that I was then being told were legal under
American law.
I'm not a lawyer but my God you have to be a complete moron
not to see that this was an illegal program.
So I declined and it was in my view so egregiously illegal
that I waited for somebody to come out and say so publicly.
Nobody did.
Two years later I resigned from the CIA and decided to go
into the private sector and I still waited for somebody
to come out and say look the CIA is torturing people.
Nobody did.
In December of 2007 Brian Ross called me from ABC News
and I knew Brian Ross by reputation.
The guy won 14 Emmy Awards and was one of the greatest
investigative journalists in America and he said he had
a source who said that I had tortured Abu Zubeda.
I said that was absolutely untrue.
I was the only person who was kind to Abu Zubeda.
I said I never laid a hand on him or on any other prisoner.
I said your source is either misinformed or he's a liar
and he said well you're welcome to come on the show
and defend yourself.
I had no idea that was a reporter's trick because
I had never spoken to a reporter before.
Well a couple of days after he asked me
President George W. Bush gave a press conference in which
he was asked about torture and he looked right in the camera
Steve and he said we do not torture like that.
I happened to be sitting on the couch with my then wife.
She was also a senior CIA officer and I looked at her
and I said he is a bald faced liar.
Now at the time on the strength of the Abu Zubeda capture
I had been promoted to be the executive assistant to the CIA's deputy director
and so I'm seeing everything that the CIA is doing everywhere in the world.
That's my job to keep the deputy director informed.
So this made me angry this statement by Bush this black
and white lie that we don't torture a few days after that
it's a Friday.
And he's walking from the South Portico of the White House
to get onto the helicopter to fly to Camp David
and a reporter shouts a question at him about torture
and he turns and he says well if there is torture
it's because of a rogue CIA officer.
And I told my wife Brian Ross's source is at the White House
and they're going to try to pin this on me.
You are listening to macro and cheese a podcast brought to you
by Real Progressives a nonprofit organization dedicated to teaching
the masses about MMD or modern monetary theory.
Please help our efforts and become a monthly donor at PayPal
or Patreon like and follow our pages on Facebook
and YouTube and follow us on Periscope Twitter Twitch
Rockfin and Instagram.
So I called Brian Ross back and I said I'll give you
your interview and I decided in the days between that phone
call and the interview itself that no matter what he asked me
I was going to tell the truth because I believed that this whole
program was illegal.
And so in December 2007 I think it was the 11th to the best
of my recollection.
I went on ABC News in a nationally televised interview
and I said three things that just changed the course of
the rest of my life.
I said that the CIA was torturing its prisoners.
I said that torture was official US government policy.
It was not the result of a rogue and I said that the policy
had been personally approved by the president himself.
As you might imagine within 24 hours the CIA filed a criminal
complaint against me with the Justice Department asking that
I be arrested for exposing classified information.
The FBI began investigating me and they investigated me for
a full year from December of 2007 to December of 2008.
And then in December 2008 they sent my attorney a letter
called the declination letter saying that they had
investigated me and they were declining to prosecute
because I had not violated the law.
The truth is it is illegal in this country to classify
a crime.
If you're committing a crime you can't make that program
classified for the purpose of keeping it from the American
people.
So I hadn't committed a crime.
Four weeks later Barack Obama takes the oath of office
as president and there's talk that he's going to name
John Brennan an old nemesis of mine from the CIA as the
CIA director.
In fact progressives were up in arms about that and
Brennan had to wait four years for the second term to become
CIA director but for the first term he became the deputy
national security advisor for counterterrorism and Brennan
asked the Justice Department to secretly reopen the case
against me.
We learned in discovery later that Brennan sent Eric Holder
a letter and he said charge him with espionage.
And Holder wrote back and said my people don't think
he committed espionage.
And then Brennan wrote back and said charge him anyway and
make him defend himself.
Wow I had no idea that my phones were tapped for the next
three years that I was being followed by teams of FBI
agents that every one of my emails was being intercepted
and then finally in January of 2012 I was arrested
and charged with five felonies including three counts of
espionage for speaking to ABC News and later on speaking
to the New York Times.
Now they knew I hadn't committed espionage and those espionage
charges were dropped eventually but not until I went bankrupt
and it's not because I was special in any way they do
this to everybody.
They do something called charge stacking where they
charge you with as many felonies as they possibly can
and then they come back and say if you take a plea
to this lesser charge we'll drop everything else.
So I was facing 45 years in prison.
Their final offer was 30 months of which I would serve 23
and it's funny they made their best and final offer
and they said I had until noon the next day to give them
an answer and my wife and I stayed up all night long
debating what to do and I decided to turn it down.
I naively said that once I get in front of a jury
they'll see how ridiculous this is.
I even hired O.J. Simpson's jury consultant who happened
to be the uncle of my best friend's wife.
We got him a security clearance and he went through
15,000 pages of classified discovery and he said listen
if we were in any other district in America I would
say let's go for it we're going to win this thing
but the Eastern District of Virginia he said your jury
is going to be made up of people from the CIA the
FBI the Pentagon and Intelligence Community contractors
you don't have a prayer.
So I still decided no I'm going to fight this thing
because I haven't done anything wrong.
Hours before I had to make the final call three of
my 11 attorneys came over to my house it was 7 o'clock
in the morning and the one that I liked and respected
the most got right up in my face and said you know
what your problem is your problem is you think
this is about justice and it's not about justice it's
about mitigating damage take the deal and I said before
I took the deal if I don't take the deal and I'm found
guilty what am I realistically looking at and they
agreed that I was realistically looking at 12 to 18 years.
Wow.
So I took the deal and it was rough it was bad.
So in the end was there any acknowledgement that your
findings were factual.
Thank you for asking that.
Six weeks before my release from prison.
I called my wife I was allowed to call her for 15
minutes every other day and I said to her how's your
day going.
She said it's great and I said yeah great why and
she said because the Senate torture report was
released today and proved that everything you said was
true and that John McCain got up on the floor of the
Senate and said that the country owed me a debt of
gratitude because if I hadn't blown the whistle on
the CIA's torture program the American people would
never have known what their government was doing
in their name and Steve's that made it all worthwhile.
Isn't that something you're not doing it for
oculage you're not doing it for money.
Nope you're doing it because you can't not do it inside
you know you got to do it.
Well exactly legacy is an important thing to me.
I don't know why I've always had this obsession with
my legacy.
I want my kids to be proud of me.
I want my grandchildren if I ever have grandchildren to
be proud of me.
Maybe I'll get hit by a bus tomorrow and my grandchildren
won't have had the opportunity to meet me.
So I want them to be able to look back and say my
grandfather was a stand up guy.
He did the right thing when history asked him to
take a position.
He took the right position.
I wasn't the only person at the CIA that was opposed to
the torture program.
There were dozens of people who were opposed to the
torture program.
So why didn't they say anything.
Why didn't anybody speak out.
I will never understand that.
But here we are now all these years later and
the cost has been very very very high.
But I can sleep at night.
I'll tell you what the biggest cost of this was after
I got out of prison.
My wife and I split up.
She elected to move on with her life with someone
else.
So I divorced her.
We've been involved in a very bitter custody battle
ever since.
And two years ago I was on the stand in court
right here in Arlington Virginia.
And my lawyer said was she a good wife and I said
oh she was an amazing wife good mother good wife.
I couldn't have made it through this ordeal without
her.
In fact she went with me to ABC News on the day
that I blew the whistle on the CIA's torture
program.
She sat just off camera and when I finished
the interview I said to her how did I do.
She said you did great.
I said yeah I didn't say anything classified
right and she said no you did great.
So then she gets called to the stand and her
lawyer says is it true that you went with him to
ABC News when he blew the whistle on the CIA's
torture program and she said yes and her lawyer
said why did you do that.
And she responded the CIA's Office of Security
asked me to go with him and report back to
them on his activities something that I continued
to do for the remainder of our marriage.
Oh my God dude we had two kids after that.
Wow and she was ratting me out to the CIA for
all those years.
Oh my God this is like total recall.
Yeah the cost was very high.
Now again with that said I can sleep at night.
I don't know what her situation is I haven't
spoken to her in three years but I can live with
myself.
I just want to put this in context.
You uncovered one big but one lie.
Yes one aspect of the CIA that Americans had no
idea about and even if they did have an idea
they couldn't get past American exceptionalism
they always find a way to make it out to be
that the good guys do what they have to do to
keep us all safe.
Right but that's just one lie how many other
state secrets and state lies are happening and
we're living in this weird world.
I hate to pull out the cliches of 1984 and the
thought police.
Sure.
Well that's a legitimate question because just
in that short period from September 11 2001
until the middle of 2005 we're talking about
a secret torture program a secret extraordinary
rendition program where people are kidnapped
and taken to countries not their own for torture
a secret prison program where there's this
archipelago of secret prisons.
There were all kinds of secrets just in that
short period of time.
We also now know from WikiLeaks thank goodness
from the vault seven revelations that the
CIA is able to take control of your car by
hacking into its computer system for the
purpose of what forcing you off a cliff
forcing you to a tree.
Killing you somehow we know that the CIA can hack
into your smart TV and turn the speaker into a
microphone so they can listen to you and what
you're saying even when the TV appears to be
off and these are just random revelations that
we've either stumbled upon or that we learned
because of whistleblowers.
What is it that we don't know it's incalculable
how much is out there that we don't know?
You know that saying it ain't what you know it's
what you think you know that just ain't so.
Yeah.
So much of the narratives that we as activists
media, alt media, families, friends.
Yeah.
So many of the things we tell each other and
we are absolutely certain we're right may have
no basis in fact or worse just enough of a
basis in fact that it retains that necessary
credibility.
You got to have a little bit of something that
ain't perfect because otherwise the brain will
reject it.
Right.
I hate to say this because I've always said
there's no way people are that organized that
they can pull this off.
I was a serial scoffer and yet as we've gone
through this my primary area of activist based
expertise is on the macroeconomic side where
we've been lied to immensely with this false
austerity narrative that we've talked about so
often and it's deprogramming and decolonizing
your brain from these lies to get to just a
base of neutrality.
Yeah.
And it's so destabilizing to think that
there's no amount of study you can really do
to understand what's being done.
A lot of this is happening off the books top
secret that will deny your existence.
How in the world could we as concerned individuals
as people who are looking for a better world a
better life when you see not only the number
one military in the world that has global
reach but then you realize that it goes deeper
than that in terms of the deep state apparatus
and spy network.
How in the world are regular people to come together?
It feels almost like hubris right to think that
we can take on this Leviathan and win.
And it feels like we're herded into voting
for people that we don't really select right
the whole damn things a charade.
The whole system is broken.
Is it broken or is that a feature?
Well, yeah, that's actually a better way to say
the system that we have is exactly the system that
the political leaders in this country want.
This is the system that they allow us to work in.
You're exactly right.
I'm a realist.
I know that the CIA is not going away.
I would hope that it would.
I don't think we need a CIA.
It causes us more trouble than it's worth.
But I know that it's not going to be abolished.
Then the only alternative is to ride our elected officials
to conduct true oversight.
But if they're in on it to and they're not willing
to conduct true oversight, then we're screwed.
There's this one senator that I mentioned who wants
to conduct oversight but is afraid of losing his
security clearances.
What about the other six or seven Democrats on the
Senate Intelligence Committee?
What's their position?
Their position is that they're in bed with the CIA.
That's why they're on the Intelligence Committee.
Wow.
I've got a whole analysis that I'm working up for my own
purposes as I dig into history and revolutionary
minded documentarian type deep dives and I constantly
find myself starting at the Bolshevik Revolution.
Not because of anything good or bad about the
Bolshevik Revolution, but it really took capitalism
by storm.
They didn't know what to do with this.
And in a recent interview I did with a brilliant
academic mind in Clara Matei.
She breaks out austerity was the response to that
period of time as World War One showed people that
there was an alternative and people started having
visions of things other than just this oppressive
capitalist system that weighs everyone down and
everything started changing right then.
Then US policy since then almost everything we've
done has been to directly counter any kind of spread
of communism.
Oh yeah.
Now I'm not necessarily preaching communism though I
am sympathetic to it.
I'm an MMT informed leftist so my politics are a
little different but not too different.
Sure.
But as I think through this they had strange bed
fellows with Joseph Stalin during World War Two but
immediately following that as they split Korea as
they went through the process of getting Japan out of
all these places that their empire had reached
everything that they have done has been with the
name of better dead than red.
And so I wonder as a CIA guy to what degree has
the CIA been instrumental in blocking socialism and
communism as a construct both internally to the US
and abroad.
Is this been a driving factor?
It's been the driving factor.
I address this at length in my fourth book.
It's called the CIA insiders guide to the Iran
crisis.
We're in crisis with Iran because of decisions that
we made in the middle 1950s to overthrow the
democratically elected government of Iran just
as one example because of our irrational obsession
with communism and it happened not just in Iran but
all over Africa in Southeast Asia which of course
led to the Vietnam War and throughout Central and
South America.
It was an irrational obsession with communism.
That's what got us into Afghanistan.
Even though the Soviet Union was weakened,
adored and humbled, we still decided that we would
rather throw our lot in with the Mujahideen than
with the Soviets and you see where it got us.
These are the pieces as I try to make sense of
US history and more importantly global history
because there's so many interrelated things
and the predation on the global south, the third
world that we have created through the programs of
oppression that we've instituted.
I often hear about how the CIA is sent in in
advance to destabilize the region to make it
right for these moments.
Yeah, but it seems to me like this is 100% the
M.O. And if that is the M.O., who is this serving?
Because communism is people ownership.
It's workers owning their means of production.
It's about an egalitarian society where there aren't
classes and rulers.
Yeah, how much does the CIA play in that?
Well, the role used to be enormous in the 50s through
the 60s into the mid 70s as technology has improved.
They've gotten away from that on the ground impact and
they do a lot of it remotely.
A lot of it still happens.
But thanks to Matt Taibi and the Twitter files, we're
seeing now that a lot of it was done through Twitter.
Remember, it was Hillary Clinton that asked Twitter
not to do its system upgrade on the night that
the so-called Green Revolution was beginning in Iran.
So the CIA is still in up to its neck.
It's just not necessarily on the ground.
The last time I can think of where there was a
significant CIA presence physically on the ground
is in the six weeks after the 9-11 attacks where we
helicoptered a dozen or so people in.
They met up with the Northern Alliance, which provided
horses. We parachuted in secure communications, millions
of dollars in cash and said, okay, overthrow the Taliban
and find Bin Laden.
And so they set out for Kabul.
Wow.
So let's put a bow on this one.
I have so many more questions, but in the spirit of,
I know you, so I'll have you back on in the future.
That's true.
If somebody listening to this is saying, wow, oh my
goodness, what is the most important thing somebody can
take away from not only your experience in jail and your
experience as a whistleblower, but overall, as they try to
process their daily lives, what would you tell them?
I would tell them that the CIA at all work for us.
The American people own this information and we have to
demand that our elected officials hold every single employee
of the CIA, every other intelligence service in our
government to account.
We own this information.
We're the bosses.
And if our elected officials are not going to conduct
legitimate oversight, then we'll elect people who will
conduct legitimate oversight.
It's that important to us.
I want to close off on that note, but I feel compelled to
say that watching what happened to Bernie Sanders,
yeah, through the 2015 primary makes the concept of
electing other people feel hollow.
I'm not voting Republican.
It's not really about voting per se.
Every time I see the Democrats rally around a corporate
stooge exactly and defend the establishment narratives and
realize how many layers of lies are stacked on top of lies.
Look what's happening with Ukraine and Russia.
Yeah, just the fact that people are so deprived of
understanding history, NATO, the IMF, they don't even
understand any of the games being played on the
international stage.
Yes.
And so it feels so hollow to think that a CIA that would run
the risk of allowing us to vote for people that are
progressives that are going to undo these things.
If we can destabilize the world and their elections,
how is it that we wouldn't make sure that we are getting
exactly what they want here as well?
Yeah, I'm glad you're raising this because I think
we need to make it very clear that the answer to these
problems does not lie in the Democratic Party.
It just doesn't.
There's no difference between the Democrats and the Republicans
on these issues.
They're just two sides of the same coin.
The problem is far bigger than just.
Well, I demand oversight.
Okay, great.
So do I, but that's not going to change anything.
We really do need viable third parties in this country.
We really do.
And God knows that we've moved backwards on this issue in
the last four decades.
I remember when I was a teenager, there was a congressman
from Illinois, John Anderson.
He ran for president against Ronald Reagan and Jimmy
Carter and he got 7%, which was dramatic.
But he got 7% because he participated in every one of
those presidential debates.
In 2000, Ralph Nader ran for president as an independent.
Before that, in 1992 and 1996, Ross Perot ran as an
independent for president, participated in the debates
and got something like, what was it, 20%.
Well, what happened was those presidential debates used
to be sponsored by the League of Women Voters independently
of the political parties.
And in the end, the political parties decided to get rid
of the League of Women Voters, create the so-called
commission on presidential debates, which is three
members of the Democratic National Committee and three
members of the Republican National Committee.
And they decided that no independent will be invited
to any presidential debate.
And so ever since that decision was taken, we don't
have third party candidates that can get national
exposure.
They're never invited to the debates.
Nobody pays any attention to them.
And the Democrats, the Republicans just trade the
presidency back and forth.
Doesn't seem like an election to me.
It seems more like a game.
Yeah, it's not a functioning democracy.
That's for sure.
No, but there in which lies my big rub on third
parties, and that is to have a third party, you got
to be able to have access to have access.
It requires the duopoly to concede that and give
it over to you.
Yeah.
And because they have control over the media,
every possible pool that capital and these establishment
elites have is used as a weapon to prevent us from
having anything other than what they want us to have.
Populism doesn't do much of anything at this point
because we have no real agency.
Yeah, to do anything with it.
And that led me to that question prior.
You got this deep state like this.
How would somebody in a modern society even pull
off a political revolution, much less a real
revolution?
Yeah, we somehow able to compartmentalize things,
but we don't synthesize the knowledge we have and
say that isn't separate.
That's all part of this.
They've got the access to everything through them that
they're not going to give up and you've got the
deep state that works to create a fake narrative.
And we have a society that is immune from actually
taking action.
And I'm trying to find my way through this maze and
all I do is keep hitting walls.
What are your thoughts there?
I don't see the light at the end of the tunnel.
If it is a light, it's probably a train coming.
Yeah.
I'd say that, but I have to agree with you.
I want to be optimistic by nature.
I am an optimistic person, but I'm just not optimistic.
Every time you think there's forward movement or
even momentum sometimes and that we might be able
to reclaim our democracy, it ends.
I don't feel like I have anything really to look
forward to politically.
Feels like a big ol' sham.
And macron cheese, we're here to make things
happen.
I'm a guy that wants to see change.
I want to change the world, but you can't change the
world by faking the world around you.
You've got to address the real problem.
And the real problem is we lack agency.
We lack the parallel systems to give us a media voice.
We lack the political clout to make a difference.
I'm just trying to make the point that you've
got a deep state, you've got a CIA, you've got a
political machine that is run by a duopoly that
doesn't allow external entrance into its game.
And then on top of it, you've got parties that are
baked into preventing any kind of change to what
they would do, baked so far into the rules that
short of a revolution, I don't know how you go
anywhere with that, but you've also got the CIA
and all the other apparatus that keeps the world
in check, waiting to keep a revolution in check.
Yeah.
It was wonderful having you on, sir.
I really appreciate it and I love that we have
a good connection.
Same here.
Please let everybody know where we can find
more of your work.
Oh, thank you.
I'm on Substack.
So it's johnkiriaku.substack.com.
Everything I write, I put on Substack.
That's the best place.
And don't forget John is a co-host of political
misfits and definitely one of my favorite posts.
I enjoy the way you do interviews.
So with that, John, I look forward to our next
conversation and for you out there, I feel it's
important to know that while we're on one hand
fighting for economic truth, we've got an entire
political system here geared up to present narratives
that just ain't sell to keep us from winning.
So we've got a lot of work to do.
John, thank you so much for joining me.
Thank you, sir.
You've got it.
This is Steve Grumbine with my guest, John
Kiriaku from Macro and Cheese.
We are out of here.
Macro and Cheese is produced by Andy Kennedy,
descriptive writing by Virginia Codds and
promotional artwork by Andy Kennedy.
Macro and Cheese is publicly funded by our
real progressive Patreon account.
If you would like to donate to Macro and Cheese,
please visit Patreon.com slash real progress.